[Music]
in 2016 washington-based lobby group
published a scientific review which
concluded that evidence in favor of
guidelines recommending limits on added
dietary sugar was low quality and did
not meet criteria for trustworthy
recommendations
this was a group funded by multinational
food and agrochemical companies from
coke to monsanto to the captains of corn
syrup accused of hijacking the
scientific process in a disingenuous way
to sow doubt and jeopardize public
health but exactly how did they get away
with it
here's their paper
questioning the scientific basis of
guideline recommendations on sugar
intake
using the grade approach they concluded
that the overall quality of evidence to
support such recommendations was low to
very low
grade stands for the grading of
recommendations assessment development
and evaluation initiative
which was developed to make clinical
guidelines more evidence-based and thank
heavens for that
clinical guidelines like which drug to
give to whom used to be developed by
like the gobset method just some good
old boys sitting round a table
under grade high quality evidence
appears to be derived exclusively from
randomized trials this is not surprising
given that the grade process was
designed for drugs and of course you
want your drugs put to the test like
remember the premarin story where for a
decade organizations recommended that
clinicians encourage postmenopausal
women to use hormone replacement therapy
because women who are taking it appeared
to have fewer heart attacks but when put
to the test randomized controlled trials
instead showed the opposite
so we definitely want drugs put through
randomized double-blind
placebo-controlled trials where people
are randomized to take the drug or
unknowingly take a placebo instead and
no one knows who's in which group until
the code is broken at the end and you
see how well the two groups did compared
to each other
everyone agrees that randomized
controlled trials are enormously
valuable in many areas of medical
research such as the testing of drugs
but wait a second how do you do that
with diet i mean there's no such thing
as a placebo diet how can you randomize
people to different diets but somehow
hide from them which diets they're
following
people tend to notice what they put into
their own mouths
and rcts randomized controlled trials
are so expensive they typically last for
only weeks or months but it takes most
cancers decades to develop so it's
nearly impossible to see if like you
know different diets prevent or cause
cancer that way
to see if smoking causes cancer you can
fall large cohorts of smokers and
non-smokers out for decades to see who
gets cancer and who doesn't but it's not
like you can randomize people to smoke
or not smoke for decades when studying
lifestyle interventions you often just
can't do randomized controlled trials
and even if you could it might not be
ethical
take crib death for example sudden
infant death syndrome a pivotal study
studying the habits of infants who died
discovered that sleeping on their
stomachs was a risk factor so he started
educating parents face up to wake up
and the sids rates dropped
what more do we need
would it even be ethical to randomize
thousands of babies to sleep on their
backs or fronts and count up the deaths
at this point you can get sufficient
evidence to make lifestyle
recommendations that save lives without
randomized controlled trials
critical questions like what dietary
pattern produces the best health
outcomes over a lifetime simply can't be
answered with randomized controlled
trials you can't randomize people to
different lifetime diets and expect them
to stick to them so we need to compile
an amalgamation of evidence from other
study designs
but the lack of evidence from randomized
controlled trials has become a common
argumentation strategy for criticizing
nutrition recommendations
similar claims were made by the tobacco
industry in its attempt to discredit
evidence on the harms of tobacco case in
point
the so-called sound science campaign
carried out by philip morris
this is all straight out of the tobacco
industry playbook philip morris used
public relations firms and lawyers to
develop a sound science program that
involved recruiting other industries and
issues to obscure the tobacco industry's
role
they tried to enshrine quote unquote
good epidemiological practices that
would make it impossible to conclude
that secondhand smoke and thus other
environmental toxins caused diseases
public health professionals need to be
aware that the sound science movement is
not an indigenous effort from within the
profession to improve the quality of
scientific discourse but rather reflects
sophisticated public relations campaigns
controlled by industry executives and
lawyers whose aim
is to manipulate the standards of
scientific proof to serve the corporate
interests of their clients and not just
tobacco clients but hopes to expand to
the food plastics and chemical
industries
philip morris went beyond just creating
doubt and controversy about the
scientific evidence to attempting to
change the scientific standards of proof
but randomized controlled trials aren't
the only source of good evidence as sir
bradford hill himself said who pioneered
the randomized control trial
any belief that the controlled trial is
the only way to go would mean not just
that the pendulum had swung too far but
that it had come right off the hook
[Music]
you